- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) State six similarities in the annunciations of the birth of John the Baptist and Jesus Christ."
      Answer:
        - "Both births were announced by Angel Gabriel"
        - "In both, their names were given before they were born"
        - "In both, their missions were given before they were born"
        - "Both were born under extraordinary circumstances"
        - "In both, signs were given to their parents"
        - "In both, the possibility of the message was doubted by Zechariah and Mary"
        - "In both, the children will be God's servants"
        - "In both, Angel Gabriel told the parents not to be afraid"
      Marks: 6
    - Subquestion: "b) With reference to Lk1:13-17, outline the message of Angel Gabriel about John to Zechariah."
      Answer:
        - "John was to be a son"
        - "His name was to be John"
        - "He would bring joy/gladness to his parents/many will rejoice at his birth"
        - "He will be great before God"
        - "He was to drink no wine/strong drink"
        - "He was to be filled with the Holy Spirit from his mother's womb"
        - "He would turn many of the sons of Israel to the Lord their God"
        - "He was to go before the Lord in the spirit/power of Elijah"
        - "He would turn the hearts of the fathers to the children and disobedient to the wisdom of the just"
        - "He was to make ready for the Lord"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "c) What lessons do Christians learn about family relationships from the incident when Jesus accompanied His parents for the Passover festival?"
      Answer:
        - "Christians should obey their parents"
        - "Parents should teach their children about God"
        - "Parents should provide opportunities for their children to mix with others"
        - "Parents should love/be concerned about their children"
        - "Family ties should not be broken/families should live in unity"
        - "God's work takes priority over family"
        - "Parents should recognize their children's talents"
        - "There should be open communication among family members"
      Marks: 7
  QuestionNumber: 1
  Marks: 20

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) With reference to the Sermon on the Plain, state five teachings of Jesus on how human beings should relate to one another."
      Answer:
        - "Human beings should love their enemies"
        - "They should do good to those who hate them"
        - "They should bless those who curse them"
        - "They should pray for those who mistreat them"
        - "Help those in need"
        - "They should lend without expecting anything in return"
        - "They should show mercy to others"
        - "They should be generous"
        - "They should forgive/not to revenge"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "b) Describe the incident in which Jesus calmed the storm. Lk 8:22-25"
      Answer:
        - "Jesus got into a boat with His disciples"
        - "He told them they should go to the other side of the lake so they set out"
        - "As they sailed, Jesus fell asleep"
        - "A storm of wind came down on the lake"
        - "The boat was filled with water"
        - "The disciples went and woke up Jesus, saying 'Master, we are drowning'"
        - "Jesus got up and rebuked the wind"
        - "The storm subsided"
        - "Jesus asked the disciples where their faith was"
        - "The disciples were afraid/they marveled"
        - "The disciples wondered who Jesus was, even the wind obey Him"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "c) Give six reasons why Christians should have faith in God."
      Answer:
        - "God fulfills the promises He makes to human beings"
        - "Those who pray in faith receive their requests"
        - "Helps Christians grow spiritually"
        - "Christians who have faith can be healed"
        - "Faith helps Christians overcome temptations"
        - "Faith helps Christians to wait patiently for the second coming"
      Marks: 6
  QuestionNumber: 2
  Marks: 20

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Give an account of Jesus' teaching on watchfulness and readiness. Luke 12:35-48."
      Answer:
        - "Believers should be dressed for His coming. V35."
        - "They should keep their lamps burning"
        - "They should be awake/alert. V36"
        - "Those who are found waiting shall be blessed"
        - "They should be prepared all the time since they don't know the time for Christ's coming. V.39"
        - "Believers should continue working until Christ comes back. V.43"
        - "The servants/believers who are drunkards/mistreat fellow workers will be punished. V45-46"
        - "Those who know what is required of them/their masters will and fail to do it will receive a severe beating. V47"
        - "Believers are supposed to respond to God according to how much they have received from Him"
        - "Those who do wrong out of ignorance will receive lesser beatings/punishment. V.48"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "b) How did Jesus celebrate the last supper with his disciples? Luke 22:14-38"
      Answer:
        - "Jesus sat with his disciples at one table"
        - "He told them that he had desired to have the meal with them"
        - "He took the cup, gave thanks and asked the disciples to share"
        - "He also took the bread, gave thanks, broke it and gave it to them"
        - "He explained to them the meaning of the bread and wine/the bread was his body/the wine was his blood that would seal the new covenant"
        - "He commanded the disciples to hold the ritual in memory of him"
        - "He informed them that he would be betrayed by one of them"
        - "He taught the disciples qualities of good leadership/humility/service to others"
        - "He told Simon that he would be tested by Satan/He informed him that he had already prayed for him"
        - "He asked Simon/Peter to strengthen others in their faith"
        - "Jesus told Peter that he would deny him three times before the cock crowed"
        - "He commanded the disciples to acquire swords/have their own provisions/personal belongings"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "c) Give six reasons why the disciples found it difficult to believe that Jesus had resurrected."
      Answer:
        - "The message was first taken to them by women who were regarded lowly in society, hence it seemed an idle talk"
        - "They had witnessed the helplessness of Jesus at the time of crucifixion, hence had lost hope in him"
        - "They had witnessed the burial/could not imagine how the stone could be rolled away from the tomb"
        - "They felt ashamed for having denied/betrayed him, hence wished it was not true"
        - "They had not understood the reading of Jesus which indicated that he would resurrect on the third day"
        - "It was a new experience they had never seen/heard of people coming back to life after death on their own"
        - "They lacked faith in the readings of Christ"
        - "They had expected a political Messiah who was to die in dignity/would not resurrect"
      Marks: 6
  QuestionNumber: 3
  Marks: 20

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Explain four ways in which the unity of believers is expressed in the Body of Christ. 1 Corinthians 12:12-26"
      Answer:
        - "St. Paul describes the believers as the body of Christ"
        - "Christ is the head of the church"
        - "The believers form the parts of the body"
        - "The body has different organs in the same way the church has different members"
        - "They all need to work together for the well-being of the church"
        - "Every part of the body is needed to make it whole/all parts are interdependent/one part cannot be without the other"
        - "The different church members are given different spiritual gifts by the Holy Spirit to carry out God's work"
        - "There should be no divisions in the church since all believers are members of the body of Christ"
        - "Believers are united through baptism in the Holy Spirit"
      Marks: 8
    - Subquestion: "b) Outline St. Paul's teaching on how the gifts of the Holy Spirit should be used in the church."
      Answer:
        - "The gifts of the Holy Spirit should be used for the common good for all"
        - "They should be used to strengthen/encourage/comfort members"
        - "They should be used to bring unity/not to discriminate/divide members"
        - "There is a need to respect/appreciate all the gifts"
        - "They should be used in an orderly way/no confusion"
        - "The gifts should be used in love"
        - "The gift of speaking in tongues should be minimized during public worship"
        - "There is a need to have interpretation of tongues for when it is meaningful/helpful"
        - "Prophecies should be carefully evaluated/weighted"
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "c) Give seven ways in which Christians prevent divisions in the church in Kenya today."
      Answer:
        - "Treating each other with love"
        - "Avoiding discriminations/segregations/tribalism in the church"
        - "Preaching/teaching the word of God/Bible truths to believers"
        - "Assisting those in problems/poor/the less fortunate/the needy"
        - "Practicing humility/avoiding arrogance"
        - "Openly discussing issues affecting the church/respecting the opinions of other people"
        - "Praying for one another/problems affecting the church"
        - "Practicing transparent leadership style"
        - "Giving financial reports within an acceptable period of time"
        - "Following the church doctrines/constitutions/manuals/educating members on church procedures"
        - "Repenting/asking for forgiveness whenever they are wrong/accepting their mistakes"
        - "Preparing budgets annually/seasonally/ensuring that the resources are well-utilized"
        - "Providing guidance and counseling"
      Marks: 7
  QuestionNumber: 4
  Marks: 20

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Outline seven similarities between traditional African and Christian teaching on marriage"
      Answer:
        - "In both marriage is seen as a social affair as many people are invited to attend the marriage feasts"
        - "In both marriage is aimed at providing mutual love"
        - "Both believe that marriage is sacred and that it is the divine will of God"
        - "In both marriage enables man and woman to have new responsibilities"
        - "Marriage promotes the social status of the new couple in both traditional and Christian societies"
        - "In both marriage brings about new ties of relationships. In both, the young couple gets new friends and relatives, e.g., brothers, sisters-in-law"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "b) Give seven problems associated with childlessness in marriage today"
      Answer:
        - "In extreme cases, it may lead to divorce"
        - "In extreme cases, it may lead to suicide, especially if the husband adversely accuses the wife of barrenness"
        - "Childless couples always feel incomplete"
        - "A man in a childless family may engage in heavy drinking to cover frustrations"
        - "Childless couples may resort to unfaithfulness to prove their fertility"
        - "Childless couples may be tempted to steal children"
        - "It is easy for childless couples to develop resentment towards children or those who have children"
        - "Many childless couples have constant conflicts within themselves because they keep blaming each other"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "c) Mention six ways through which Christians can resolve misunderstandings between parents and their children"
      Answer:
        - "By Christians being role models to be followed"
        - "Through prayers, Christians can bring proper understanding"
        - "Christians can provide guidance and counseling to both children and their parents"
        - "Christians can solve misunderstandings by being frank in their judgments"
        - "By committing children to God's will"
        - "By seeking help from church ministers"
      Marks: 6
  QuestionNumber: 5
  Marks: 20

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Outline seven ways how law, order and justice is maintained in Traditional African communities today"
      Answer:
        - "Punishment of offenders"
        - "Installation of rulers, Kings, Chiefs, and elders"
        - "Administration of oaths"
        - "Making of covenants"
        - "Observing taboos"
        - "Intermarriages"
        - "Sharing meals"
        - "Returning the spoils from raids"
        - "Sending emissaries/mediators to solve issues and unite warring groups"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "b) Outline seven roles played by the church to alleviate poverty in Kenya"
      Answer:
        - "Offering training to the members"
        - "Supporting the education of its youth"
        - "Building schools and vocational training centers"
        - "Giving financial and material support to the poor"
        - "Guiding and counseling on proper use of wealth"
        - "Providing biblical teachings on wealth and poverty"
        - "Condemning evils related to wealth and poverty"
        - "Conducting seminars on creating and proper use of wealth"
      Marks: 7
    - Subquestion: "c) Give six reasons why Christians should declare their wealth"
      Answer:
        - "It is a requirement by the law"
        - "It ensures smooth collection of taxes"
        - "It enhances transparency and accountability"
        - "It ensures equitable distribution of wealth resources"
        - "It sets a good example for others to emulate"
        - "It promotes harmony in the society and family"
        - "It clears one for public office"
        - "It prepares the basis for future establishment"
      Marks: 6
  QuestionNumber: 6
  Marks: 20